<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <array name="bibleIndex">
        <item>1 When God Made Everything</item>
       <item>2 The Start of Man's Sadness</item>
       <item>3 Noah and the Great Flood</item>
       <item>4 God's Promise to Abraham</item>
       <item>5 God Tests Abraham's Love</item>
       <item>6 Jacob the Deceiver</item>
       <item>7 A Favorite Son Becomes a Slave</item>
       <item>8 God Honors Joseph the Slave</item>
       <item>9 The Prince From the River</item>
       <item>10 The Prince Becomes a Shepherd</item>
       <item>11 Goodbye Pharaoh	Story</item>
       <item>12 Forty Years	Story</item>
       <item>13 Joshua Takes Charge</item>
       <item>14 Samson, God's Strong Man</item>
       <item>15 Gideon's Little Army</item>
       <item>16 Ruth - A Love Story</item>
       <item>17 Samuel, God's Boy-Servant</item>
       <item>18 The Handsome Foolish King</item>
       <item>19 David the Shepherd Boy</item>
       <item>20 David the King (Part 1)</item>
       <item>21 David the King (Part 2)</item>
       <item>22 Wise King Solomon</item>
       <item>23 Good Kings, Bad Kings</item>
       <item>24 The Man of Fire</item>
       <item>25 Elisha, Man of Miracles</item>
       <item>26 Jonah and the Big Fish</item>
       <item>27 Isaiah Sees the Future</item>
       <item>28 Jeremiah, Man of Tears</item>
       <item>29 Ezekiel: Man of Visions</item>
       <item>30 Beautiful Queen Esther</item>
       <item>31 Daniel the Captive</item>
       <item>32 Daniel and the Mystery Dream</item>
       <item>33 The Men Who Would Not Bend</item>
       <item>34 Daniel and the Lions' Den</item>
       <item>35 The Great Wall of Nehemiah</item>
       <item>36 The Birth of Jesus</item>
       <item>37 A Man Sent From God</item>
       <item>38 A Terrible Time for Jesus</item>
       <item>39 Jesus Chooses 12 Helpers</item>
       <item>40 The Miracles of Jesus</item>
       <item>41 A Temple Leader Visits Jesus</item>
       <item>42 Jesus the Great Teacher</item>
       <item>43 The Farmer and the Seed</item>
       <item>44 Rich Man, Poor Man</item>
       <item>45 The Prodigal Son	Story</item>
       <item>46 The Good Samaritan</item>
       <item>47 The Woman at the Well</item>
       <item>48 Jesus Stills the Stormy Sea</item>
       <item>49 The Girl Who Lived Twice</item>
       <item>50 Jesus Heals the Blind</item>
       <item>51 Jesus Feeds 5000 People</item>
       <item>52 Jesus and Lazarus</item>
       <item>53 Jesus and Zaccheus</item>
       <item>54 The First Easter	Story</item>
       <item>55 The Birth of the Church</item>
       <item>56 The Church Meets Trouble</item>
       <item>57 Peter and the Power of Prayer</item>
       <item>58 From Persecutor to Preacher</item>
       <item>59 Paul's Amazing Travels	</item>
       <item>60 Heaven, God's Beautiful Home</item>


    </array>



    <array name="bibleGenesis">
        <item>1 Genesis 1 New King James Version (NKJV)\n
         \n The History of Creation
         \n 1 In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth. 2 The earth was without form, and void; and darkness [a]was on the face of the deep. And the Spirit of God was hovering over the face of the waters.

         \n 3 Then God said, “Let there be light”; and there was light. 4 And God saw the light, that it was good; and God divided the light from the darkness. 5 God called the light Day, and the darkness He called Night. [b]So the evening and the morning were the first day.

         \n 6 Then God said, “Let there be a [c]firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters.” 7 Thus God made the firmament, and divided the waters which were under the firmament from the waters which were above the firmament; and it was so. 8 And God called the firmament Heaven. So the evening and the morning were the second day.

         \n 9 Then God said, “Let the waters under the heavens be gathered together into one place, and let the dry land appear”; and it was so. 10 And God called the dry land Earth, and the gathering together of the waters He called Seas. And God saw that it was good.

         \n 11 Then God said, “Let the earth bring forth grass, the herb that yields seed, and the fruit tree that yields fruit according to its kind, whose seed is in itself, on the earth”; and it was so. 12 And the earth brought forth grass, the herb that yields seed according to its kind, and the tree that yields fruit, whose seed is in itself according to its kind. And God saw that it was good. 13 So the evening and the morning were the third day.

         \n 14 Then God said, “Let there be lights in the firmament of the heavens to divide the day from the night; and let them be for signs and seasons, and for days and years; 15 and let them be for lights in the firmament of the heavens to give light on the earth”; and it was so. 16 Then God made two great [d]lights: the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night. He made the stars also. 17 God set them in the firmament of the heavens to give light on the earth, 18 and to rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkness. And God saw that it was good. 19 So the evening and the morning were the fourth day.

         \n 20 Then God said, “Let the waters abound with an abundance of living [e]creatures, and let birds fly above the earth across the face of the [f]firmament of the heavens.” 21 So God created great sea creatures and every living thing that moves, with which the waters abounded, according to their kind, and every winged bird according to its kind. And God saw that it was good. 22 And God blessed them, saying, “Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let birds multiply on the earth.” 23 So the evening and the morning were the fifth day.

         \n 24 Then God said, “Let the earth bring forth the living creature according to its kind: cattle and creeping thing and beast of the earth, each according to its kind”; and it was so. 25 And God made the beast of the earth according to its kind, cattle according to its kind, and everything that creeps on the earth according to its kind. And God saw that it was good.

         \n 26 Then God said, “Let Us make man in Our image, according to Our likeness; let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, over the birds of the air, and over the cattle, over [g]all the earth and over every creeping thing that creeps on the earth.” 27 So God created man in His own image; in the image of God He created him; male and female He created them. 28 Then God blessed them, and God said to them, “Be fruitful and multiply; fill the earth and subdue it; have dominion over the fish of the sea, over the birds of the air, and over every living thing that [h]moves on the earth.”

            \n  29 And God said, “See, I have given you every herb that yields seed which is on the face of all the earth, and every tree whose fruit yields seed; to you it shall be for food. 30 Also, to every beast of the earth, to every bird of the air, and to everything that creeps on the earth, in which there is [i]life, I have given every green herb for food”; and it was so. 31 Then God saw everything that He had made, and indeed it was very good. So the evening and the morning were the sixth day.</item>
        <item>Genesis 6 New King James Version (NKJV) \n
         \n  The Wickedness and Judgment of Man
         \n  6 Now it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth, and daughters were born to them, 2 that the sons of God saw the daughters of men, that they were beautiful; and they took wives for themselves of all whom they chose.

         \n  3 And the Lord said, “My Spirit shall not strive[a] with man forever, for he is indeed flesh; yet his days shall be one hundred and twenty years.” 4 There were [b]giants on the earth in those days, and also afterward, when the sons of God came in to the daughters of men and they bore children to them. Those were the mighty men who were of old, men of renown.

         \n  5 Then [c]the Lord saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that every intent[d] of the thoughts of his heart was only evil [e]continually. 6 And the Lord was sorry that He had made man on the earth, and He was grieved in His heart. 7 So the Lord said, “I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth, both man and beast, creeping thing and birds of the air, for I am sorry that I have made them.” 8 But Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.

         \n  Noah Pleases God
         \n  9 This is the genealogy of Noah. Noah was a just man, [f]perfect in his generations. Noah walked with God. 10 And Noah begot three sons: Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

         \n  11 The earth also was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence. 12 So God looked upon the earth, and indeed it was corrupt; for all flesh had corrupted their way on the earth.

         \n  The Ark Prepared
         \n  13 And God said to Noah, “The end of all flesh has come before Me, for the earth is filled with violence through them; and behold, I will destroy them with the earth. 14 Make yourself an ark of gopherwood; make [g]rooms in the ark, and cover it inside and outside with pitch. 15 And this is how you shall make it: The length of the ark shall be three hundred [h]cubits, its width fifty cubits, and its height thirty cubits. 16 You shall make a window for the ark, and you shall finish it to a cubit from above; and set the door of the ark in its side. You shall make it with lower, second, and third decks. 17 And behold, I Myself am bringing floodwaters on the earth, to destroy from under heaven all flesh in which is the breath of life; everything that is on the earth shall die. 18 But I will establish My covenant with you; and you shall go into the ark—you, your sons, your wife, and your sons’ wives with you. 19 And of every living thing of all flesh you shall bring two of every sort into the ark, to keep them alive with you; they shall be male and female. 20 Of the birds after their kind, of animals after their kind, and of every creeping thing of the earth after its kind, two of every kind will come to you to keep them alive. 21 And you shall take for yourself of all food that is eaten, and you shall gather it to yourself; and it shall be food for you and for them.”

         \n  22 Thus Noah did; according to all that God commanded him, so he did.</item>
        <item>3 Noah and the Great Flood</item>
        <item>4 God's Promise to Abraham</item>
        <item>5 God Tests Abraham's Love</item>
        <item>6 Jacob the Deceiver</item>
        <item>7 A Favorite Son Becomes a Slave</item>
        <item>8 God Honors Joseph the Slave</item>
        <item>9 The Prince From the River</item>
        <item>10 The Prince Becomes a Shepherd</item>
        <item>11 Goodbye Pharaoh	Story</item>
        <item>12 Forty Years	Story</item>
        <item>13 Joshua Takes Charge</item>
        <item>14 Samson, God's Strong Man</item>
        <item>15 Gideon's Little Army</item>
        <item>16 Ruth - A Love Story</item>
        <item>17 Samuel, God's Boy-Servant</item>
        <item>18 The Handsome Foolish King</item>
        <item>19 David the Shepherd Boy</item>
        <item>20 David the King (Part 1)</item>
        <item>21 David the King (Part 2)</item>
        <item>22 Wise King Solomon</item>
        <item>23 Good Kings, Bad Kings</item>
        <item>24 The Man of Fire</item>
        <item>25 Elisha, Man of Miracles</item>
        <item>26 Jonah and the Big Fish</item>
        <item>27 Isaiah Sees the Future</item>
        <item>28 Jeremiah, Man of Tears</item>
        <item>29 Ezekiel: Man of Visions</item>
        <item>30 Beautiful Queen Esther</item>
        <item>31 Daniel the Captive</item>
        <item>32 Daniel and the Mystery Dream</item>
        <item>33 The Men Who Would Not Bend</item>
        <item>34 Daniel and the Lions' Den</item>
        <item>35 The Great Wall of Nehemiah</item>
        <item>36 The Birth of Jesus</item>
        <item>37 A Man Sent From God</item>
        <item>38 A Terrible Time for Jesus</item>
        <item>39 Jesus Chooses 12 Helpers</item>
        <item>40 The Miracles of Jesus</item>
        <item>41 A Temple Leader Visits Jesus</item>
        <item>42 Jesus the Great Teacher</item>
        <item>43 The Farmer and the Seed</item>
        <item>44 Rich Man, Poor Man</item>
        <item>45 The Prodigal Son	Story</item>
        <item>46 The Good Samaritan</item>
        <item>47 The Woman at the Well</item>
        <item>48 Jesus Stills the Stormy Sea</item>
        <item>49 The Girl Who Lived Twice</item>
        <item>50 Jesus Heals the Blind</item>
        <item>51 Jesus Feeds 5000 People</item>
        <item>52 Jesus and Lazarus</item>
        <item>53 Jesus and Zaccheus</item>
        <item>54 The First Easter	Story</item>
        <item>55 The Birth of the Church</item>
        <item>56 The Church Meets Trouble</item>
        <item>57 Peter and the Power of Prayer</item>
        <item>58 From Persecutor to Preacher</item>
        <item>59 Paul's Amazing Travels	</item>
        <item>60 Heaven, God's Beautiful Home</item>


    </array>









</resources>

